Today we're going to talk about sorting,
今天我们讨论排序
which may not come as such a big surprise.
这对大家来说也许并不意外
We talked about sorting for a while,
因为我们已经研究排序好一阵子了
but we're going to talk about it at a somewhat higher level
但今天我们将会更加深入地探讨一下
and question some of the assumptions
并对我们先前作出的有些假设
that we've been making so far.
提出一些疑问
And we're going to ask the question how fast can we sort?
现在我有一个问题 排序最快可以多快
A pretty natural question.
一个很自然的问题
You may think you know the answer.
你们可能认为自己知道答案
Perhaps you do.
也许你们知道
Any suggestions on what the answer to this question might be?
谁知道这答案是多少
There are several possible answers.
答案不是唯一的
Many of them are partially correct.
很多答案都会在一定程度上正确
Let's hear any kinds of answers you'd like
所以 请大家畅所欲言吧
and start waking up this fresh morning.
让大脑从早晨的迷糊中逐渐清醒过来
Sorry?
什么
Theta n log n.
Θ(nlgn)
That's a good answer.
这个答案不错
That's often correct.
也是比较容易想到的答案
Any other suggestions?
还有其他答案吗
n squared.
n的平方
That's correct if all you're allowed to do is swap adjacent elements.
只允许进行相邻数字交换时这个答案正确
Good.
不错
That was close.
这答案也不错
I will see if I can make every answer correct.
看看我能不能给出所有答案成立的条件
Usually n squared is not the right answer, but in some models it is.
通常只在特定条件下n的平方才会是正解
Yeah?
请说
Theta n is also sometimes the right answer.
Θ(n)同样只在特定条件下才成立
The real answer is "it depends".
所以 真正的答案要“看情况”
That's the point of today's lecture.
这就是今天的观点
It depends on what we call the computational model,
它取决于你使用的计算模型里
what you're allowed to do.
哪些操作是被允许的
And, in particular here, with sorting,
当然 这里是指 就排序来说
what we care about is the order of the elements,
我们关心的是元素的排列顺序
how are you allowed to manipulate the elements,
我们可以如何对元素操作
what are you allowed to do with them and find out their order.
在排序过程中 哪些操作是被允许的
The model is what you can do with the elements.
模型简单来说就是那些你被允许的操作
Now, we've seen several sorting algorithms.
至今为止我们已经学过好几种排序算法
Do you want to shout some out?
能大声地说出来有哪些吗
I think we've seen four, but maybe you know even more algorithms.
我记得的有4种 但你们可能知道更多
Quicksort.
快速排序
Keep going.
继续
Heapsort.
堆排序
Merge sort.
归并排序
You can remember all the way back to Lecture 1.
你们还记得第一讲的内容
Any others?
还有吗
Insertion sort.
插入排序
All right.
好的
You're on top of it today.
你们对这些算法都很熟悉
I don't know exactly why, but these two are single words
我不知道为什么这两个算法只有一个单词
and these two are two words.
而下面两个算法要用两个单词表示
That's the style.
但风格就是这样
What is the running time of quicksort?
快速排序的运行时间是多少
This is a bit tricky.
看起来这个问题有点难
N log n in the average case.
平均情况下运行时间是nlgn
Or, if we randomize quicksort,
或者说 如果我们随机化快速排序
randomized quicksort runs in n log n expected for any input sequence.
随机化的快速排序运行时间为nlgn
Let's say n lg n randomized.
所以说在被随机化时是nlgn
That's theta.
前面带个Θ
And the worst-case with plain old quicksort
而最初的朴素快速排序的最差情况是
where you just pick the first element as the partition element.
在取第一个元素作为分块元素时发生
That's n^2.
运行时间是n的平方
Heapsort, what's the running time there?
堆排序呢 运行时间是多少
n lg n always.
永远是nlgn
Merge sort, I hope you can remember that as well, n lg n.
归并排序 希望你们还记得 也是nlgn
And insertion sort? n^2.
插入排序呢 n的平方
All of these algorithms run no faster than n lg n,
这些算法运行时间都没有小于nlgn的
so we might ask, can we do better than n lg n?
于是我想问 运行时间可能小于nlgn吗
And that is a question, in some sense,
事实上这个问题答案 在一定程度上说
we will answer both yes and no to today.
亦是亦非
But all of these algorithms have something in common in terms of
以上算法在规范操作的模型中
the model of what you're allowed to do with the elements.
都存在一些共同点
Any guesses on what that model might be?
大家对这个模型有什么猜想吗
Yeah? You compare pairs of elements, exactly.
请说 你只能对2个元素进行比较 没错
That is indeed the model used by all four of these algorithms.
这就是四个算法共用的模型
And in that model n lg n is the best you can do.
在这个模型中 nlgn是最快的
We have so far just looked at what are called comparison sorting algorithms
现在来看一下叫做比较排序的算法模型
or "comparison sorts".
或者直接说比较排序
And this is a model for the sorting problem of what you're allowed to do.
这是解决排序问题的一个模型
Here all you can do is use comparisons meaning less than, greater than,
在模型中 你只能做比较操作: 小于
less than or equal to, greater than or equal to,
大于 小于等于 大于等于和等于
equals to determine the relative order of elements.
来决定元素的相对顺序
This is a restriction on algorithms.
这是这个算法的局限
It is, in some sense, stating what kinds of elements we're dealing with.
在某种意义上也说明了要处理的元素类型
They are elements that we can somehow compare.
这些元素是可以进行比较操作的
They have a total order, some are less, some are bigger.
它们最终会有一个顺序 有小有大
But is also restricts the algorithm.
但也对算法本身产生了约束
You could say, well, I'm sorting integers,
举个例子来说 我对整数进行排序
but still I'm only allowed to do comparisons with them.
但我只能进行比较的操作
I'm not allowed to multiply the integers or do other weird things.
我不能进行整数相乘或者其他奇怪的操作
That's the comparison sorting model.
这就是比较排序模型
And this lecture, in some sense,
一定程度上来说 这一讲会遵循
follows the standard mathematical progression where you have a theorem,
标准数学逻辑方式 当你想到一个定理
then you have a proof, then you have a counter example.
你要先证明这个定理 然后寻找反例
It's always a good way to have a math lecture.
在涉及数学的课上这样做不失为一件好事
We're going to prove the theorem
接下来就要证明我们的这个定理:
that no comparison sorting algorithm runs better than n lg n.
比较排序的算法运算速度不会快于nlgn
Comparisons.
比较排序
State the theorem, prove that,
提出定理 证明它
and then we'll give a counter example in the sense
然后再举个反例
that if you go outside the comparison sorting model you can do better,
在不用比较排序时运算速度可以快于nlgn
you can get linear time in some cases, better than n lg n.
在某些条件下你甚至可以得到n 快于nlgn
So, that is what we're doing today.
所以 这就是我们今天要做的事
But first we're going to stick to this comparison model
首先 我们来看一下这个比较模型
and try to understand
并进而理解为什么
why we need n lg n comparisons if that's all we're allowed to do.
在只允许比较操作时最少需要nlgn次操作
And for that we're going to look at something
先看一个被叫做
called decision trees,
决策树的东西
which in some sense is another model of
可以说它是算法里另一个
what you're allowed to do in an algorithm,
规定你可以进行哪些操作的模型
but it's more general than the comparison model.
但这比比较模型适用范围更广
And let's try and example to get some intuition.
我们举个例子让它更加直观
Suppose we want to sort three elements.
假设需要对3个元素进行排序
This is not very challenging,
这并不是很有挑战性
but we'll get to draw the decision tree
但这里我们将通过绘制决策树的方法
that corresponds to sorting three elements.
来实现对3个元素排序
Here is one solution I claim.
下面是我的一种解法
This is, in a certain sense, an algorithm,
这也可以被看做是一种算法
but it's drawn as a tree instead of pseudocode.
只不过不是用伪代码而是用决策树来实现
What this tree means is that each node you're making a comparison.
树上的每一个节点表示一次比较操作
This says compare a_1 versus a_2.
这里是比较a₁和a₂
If a_1 is smaller than a_2 you go this way,
如果a₁<a₂ 走这条路
if it is bigger than a_2 you go this way, and then you proceed.
如果a₁>a₂ 走这条路 然后继续前进
When you get down to a leaf, this is the answer.
当你抵达一个叶节点 就得到了一个答案
Remember, the sorting problem is you're trying to
记住 排序问题是需要你
find a permutation of the inputs that puts it in sorted order.
找到一个对输入序列实现排序输出的方法
Let's try it with some sequence of numbers, say 9, 4 and 6.
我们用一组序列来试一下: 9 4 6
We want to sort 9, 4 and 6,
对9 4 6进行排序
so first we compare the first element with the second element.
首先 比较a₁和a₂的大小
9 is bigger than 4 so we go down this way.
9比4大 我们选择这边的路径
Then we compare the first element with the third element,
然后 比较a₁和a₃的大小
that's 9 versus 6.
9与6比较
9 is bigger than 6, so we go this way.
9大于6 所以往这边走
And then we compare the second element with the third element,
之后 我们比较a₂和a₃的大小
4 is less than 6 and, so we go this way.
4小于6 往这边走
And the claim is that this is the correct permutation of the elements.
于是说 这就是元素的正确排序
You take a_2, which is 4, then you take a_3,
第一个是a₂ 值是4 第二个是a₃
which is 6, and then you take a_1, which is 9, so indeed that works out.
值是6 之后是a₁ 值是9 算法有效
And if I wrote this down right,
如果我没有抄错的话
this is a sorting algorithm in the decision tree model.
这就是决策树模型下的排序算法
In general, let me just say the rules of this game.
一般地 游戏规则是这样的
In general, we have n elements we want to sort.
通常 会有n个元素需要排序
And I only drew the n = 3 case
这里只是做了n=3的情况
because these trees get very big very quickly.
这是因为决策树会成长得很快
Each internal node, so every non-leaf node,
每一个内节点 即每一个非叶节点
has a label of the form i : j where i and j are between 1 and n.
都会有一个下标i:j i和j分别在1到n之间
And this means that we compare a_i with a_j.
这表示我们要比较ai和aj的大小
And we have two subtrees from every such node.
每个内节点下会分出2棵子树
We have the left subtree which tells you what the algorithm does,
左边的子树说明ai<aj的情况下
what subsequent comparisons it makes if it comes out less than.
算法要做什么 后续会进行哪些比较
And we have to be a little bit careful
这里我们需要留心
because it could also come out equal.
两数比较结果可能会是相等
What we will do is the left subtree corresponds to less than or equal to
所以 左边的子树对应小于等于条件
and the right subtree corresponds to strictly greater than.
右边的子树对应大于的情况
That is a little bit more precise than what we were doing here.
因此 这里会比刚才的例子更严谨
Here all the elements were distinct so no problem.
这里的数是不等的 所以没有出现问题
But, in general, we care about the equality case too to be general.
但为了更通用 必须考虑相等的情况
So, that was the internal nodes.
好的 这就是内节点的设定
And then each leaf node gives you a permutation.
而每一个叶节点代表一个排序
So, in order to be the answer to that sorting problem,
若某个排序是正解
that permutation better have the property that it orders the elements.
则这个排序更好地表达了数的特定排列
This is from the first lecture when we defined the sorting problem.
也就是在第一讲里我们对排序问题的定义
Some permutation on n things such that a_pi(1) is less than
排列使得aπ(1)小于等于
or equal to a_pi(2) and so on.
aπ(2) 依此类推
So, that is the definition of a decision tree.
那么 这就是决策树的定义
Any binary tree with these kinds of labels satisfies all these properties.
任何与之相似的二分树都满足这些特征
That is, in some sense, a sorting algorithm.
这可以说是一种排序算法
It's a sorting algorithm in the decision tree model.
在决策树模型下的排序算法
Now, as you might expect,
正如你们可能想到的
this is really not too different than the comparison model.
决策树模型和比较模型其实相差不大
If I give you a comparison sorting algorithm,
如果给你一个比较排序算法
we have these four, quicksort, heapsort, merge sort and insertion sort.
快排 堆排序 归并排序或者插入排序
All of them can be translated into the decision tree model.
这4种都可以被转换成决策树模型的方式
It's sort of a graphical representation of what the algorithm does.
这是算法的一种图形表示
It's not a terribly useful one for writing down an algorithm.
但在写算法的时候这种表达不是非常有用
Any guesses why?
猜猜看为什么
Why do we not draw these pictures as a definition of quicksort
为什么不能通过绘制图形的方式定义快排
or a definition of merge sort?
或者定义归并排序呢
It depends on the size of the input, that's a good point.
因为它取决于输入的大小 不错的观点
This tree is specific to the value of n, so it is,
这棵树因n的数值而有不同的大小
in some sense, not as generic.
所以某种意义上来说 不具有一般性
Now, we could try to write down a construction for
接下来 我们将尝试写一个
an arbitrary value of n of one of these decision trees
表示任意n值的决策树
and that would give us sort of a real algorithm
它会是一个对任意n都成立的
that works for any input size.
真正的算法
But even then this is not a terribly convenient representation
即便如此 这仍不是一个很方便的表达
for writing down an algorithm.
在用于记录一个算法方面
Well, let's write down a transformation
现在 我将把比较排序的一个算法
that converts a comparison sorting algorithm to a decision tree
转换成决策树形式的算法表达
and then maybe you will see why.
之后 也许你就会知道为什么了
This is not a useless model,
但这不是一个无用的模型
obviously, I wouldn't be telling you otherwise.
这显然不是无用的 我永远不会这么说
It will be very powerful for proving
无论如何它在证明我们找不到
that we cannot do better than n lg n,
快于nlgn的算法时显得十分有效
but as writing down an algorithm,
但在记录一个算法时 如果想要
if you were going to implement something, this tree is not so useful.
某些功能 这棵树就不是很有用
Even if you had a decision tree computer, whatever that is.
即使专门用一台计算机来处理决策树也一样
But let's prove this theorem that decision trees,
那么 让我们用决策树的表达方式
in some sense, model comparison sorting algorithms,
构建比较排序算法
which we call just comparison sorts.
或者直接叫做比较排序
This is a transformation.
下面是转换的过程
And we're going to build one tree for each value of n.
我们将会为每一个n值绘制一棵决策树
The decision trees depend on n.
因为决策树和n值有关
The algorithm hopefully, well, it depends on n,
虽然与n有关 但我们希望这个算法
but it works for all values of n.
对所有的n都有效
And we're just going to think of the algorithm as splitting into two forks,
进行比较时 我们把树分成两个分支
the left subtree and the right subtree whenever it makes a comparison.
左子树和右子树
If we take a comparison sort like merge sort.
如果使用归并排序算法
And it does lots of stuff.
需要进行很多操作
It does index arithmetic, it does recursion, whatever.
比如算数平均 还有递归等等
But at some point it makes a comparison and then we say,
但终归要进行比较 所以我们可以说
OK, there are two halves of the algorithm.
我们把算法分成了两部分
There is what the algorithm would do
当比较结果是小于等于时
if the comparison came out less than or equal to
算法会做哪些操作
and what the algorithm would do if the comparison came out greater than.
当结果为大于等于时 算法又会做什么
So, you can build a tree in this way.
所以 你可以用这种方式构建这棵树
In some sense, what this tree is doing is listing all possible executions
可以说 决策树就是把算法中这些比较的
of this algorithm considering
所有可能的结果
what would happen for all possible values of those comparisons.
分别列出来
We will call these all possible instruction traces.
也可以说决策树指出了所有可能的路线
If you write down all the instructions that are executed by this algorithm,
如果你把算法的执行过程画出来
for all possible input arrays, a_1 to a_n, see what all the comparisons,
包括算法的输入 从a₁到an
how they could come and what the algorithm does,
还有比较过程
in the end you will get a tree.
最后就得到一个决策树
Now, how big will that tree be roughly?
那么 猜一猜这个决策树到底有多大呢
As a function of n.
是n的一个函数
Yeah? Good.
请说 很好
If it's got to be able to sort every possible list of length n,
如果算法对长度为n的任意序列都能排序
at the leaves I have to have all the permutations of those elements.
叶节点就是这些元素所有可能的顺序
That is a lot.
这个值会很大
There are a lot of permeations on n elements.
n个元素的所有排列是很大的值
There's n factorial of them.
这个值等于n的阶乘
N factorial is exponential, it's really big.
n的阶乘是指数级 的确很大
So, this tree is huge.
所以 这个决策树也很大
It's going to be exponential on the input size n.
输入规模为n 结果就是指数级
That is why we don't write algorithms down normally as a decision tree,
这就是为什么一般不用决策树来描述算法
even though in some cases maybe we could.
即使我们能将决策树画出来
It's not a very compact representation.
这不是一种简洁的表达方式
These algorithms, you write them down in pseudocode,
用伪代码描述算法
they have constant length.
一个好处就是长度固定
It's a very succinct representation of this algorithm.
伪代码是一种非常简洁的算法描述方式
Here the length depends on n
伪代码的长度只跟n有关
and it depends exponentially on n,
而决策树跟n的阶乘有关
which is not useful if you wanted to implement the algorithm
用决策树来描述算法显然很不方便
because writing down the algorithm would take a long time.
因为光画决策树就很费时了
But, nonetheless,
但是 我们也要注意到
we can use this as a tool to analyze these comparison sorting algorithms.
决策树分析这些比较排序算法时却很有用
We have all of these.
我们现在学到这些算法
Any algorithm can be transformed in this way into a decision tree.
每一个都可以转换成决策树的描述方式
And now we have this observation
现在我们知道在一个决策树中
that the number of leaves in this decision tree has to be really big.
叶节点的个数是非常多的
Let me talk about leaves in a second.
我马上就要说到叶节点
Before we get to leaves, let's talk about the depth of the tree.
在那之前 先了解一下树的深度这个概念
This decision tree represents all possible executions of the algorithm.
决策树代表算法执行的所有可能
If I look at a particular execution,
如果我挑出一条特定的算法执行路径
which corresponds to some root to leaf path in the tree,
它就对应一条从根节点到叶节点的路径
the running time or the number of comparisons made by
算法执行路径的运行时间 比较次数
that execution is just the length of the path.
就是对应决策树路径的深度
And, therefore, the worst-case running time,
因此 对于长为n的所有可能输入
over all possible inputs of length n, is going to be --
最坏情况运行时间等于
n - 1? Could be.
n-1吗 可能
Depends on the decision tree.
这得看决策树是什么样的
But, as a function of the decision tree?
和决策树的什么有关呢
The longest path, right, which is called the height of the tree.
最长路径 正确 也就是树的高度
So, this is what we want to measure.
这就是我们要讲的
We want to claim that the height of the tree
我们想要证明树的深度
has to be at least n lg n with an omega in front.
最小值是Ω(nlgn)
That is what we'll prove.
这就是我们要证明的
And the only thing we're going to use is that the number of leaves
我们唯一能用到的证明条件是
in that tree has to be big, has to be n factorial.
叶节点的数目很大 是n的阶乘
This is a lower bound on decision tree sorting.
这是决策树排序的下界
And the lower bound says that
下界的意思就是说
if you have any decision tree that sorts n elements
如果决策树是针对n个元素排序
then its height has to be at least n lg n up to constant factors.
那么它的高度至少是nlgn
So, that is the theorem.
这是一个定理
Now we're going to prove the theorem.
下面我们来证明这个定理
And we're going to use that the number of leaves in that tree
用到的条件是 决策树中叶节点
must be at least n factorial.
的个数至少是n的阶乘
Because there are n factorial permutations of the inputs.
因为输入值的所有排列个数是n的阶乘
All of them could happen.
各种排列都可能发生
And so, for this algorithm to be correct,
所以 一个合理的算法
it has detect every one of those permutations in some way.
必须以某种方式检测每种排列情况
Now, it may do it very quickly.
算法也许能很快的检测所有情况
We better only need n lg n comparisons
理想的情况是只比较nlgn次
because we know that's possible.
我们知道这是可能的
The depth of the tree may not be too big,
树的高度可能不会太深
but it has to have a huge number of leaves down there.
但它可能有非常多的叶子
It has to branch enough to get n factorial leaves
决策树必须极力延伸出n的阶乘个叶子
because it has to give the right answer in possible inputs.
因为它必须针对每种输入都得出正确答案
This is, in some sense, counting the number of possible inputs
这个过程也可以看做是
that we have to distinguish.
计算所有可能输入序列的数目
This is the number of leaves.
这是叶节点个数
What we care about is the height of the tree.
我们关心的是树的高度
Let's call the height of the tree h.
设树的高度为h
Now, if I have a tree of height h, how many leaves could it have?
一个高度为h的树的叶节点个数是多少
What's the maximum number of leaves it could have? 2^h, exactly.
叶子个数最大是多少 2^h 完全正确
Because this is binary tree,
因为这是一个二叉树
comparison trees always have a branching factor of 2,
基于比较的树都有两个分支
the number of leaves has to be at most 2^h, if I have a height h tree.
树的高度是h时叶子个数最大就是2^h
Now, this gives me a relation.
现在我们得到一个推导关系
The number of leaves has to be greater than or equal to n factorial
叶子个数大于或等于n的阶乘
and the number of leaves has to be less than or equal to 2^h.
并且 叶子个数还小于等于2^h
Therefore, n factorial is less than or equal to 2^h, if I got that right.
因此就有 n的阶乘小于或等于2^h
Now, again, we care about h in terms of n factorial,
我们关心的是h和n的阶乘之间的关系
so we solve this by taking logs.
可以引入lg运算来解决这个问题
And I am also going to flip sides.
我把两边互换一下
Now h is at least log base 2,
h大于等于
because there is a 2 over here, of n factorial.
lg(n!) 这里lg的底数为2
There is a property that I'm using here
这里我用到了一个不等式的性质
in order to derive this inequality from this inequality.
它可以从这个不等式推出这个不等式
This is a technical aside,
这不是我们课程要讲的东西
but it's important that you realize there is a technical issue here.
但你必须知道这是一个很重要的性质
The general principle I'm applying is I have some inequality,
基本原则是我有一个不等式
I do the same thing to both sides,
对一个不等式的两边做同样的运算
and hopefully that inequality should still be true.
我们希望 得到的不等式仍然成立
But, in order for that to be the case,
为了得到上面这个结果
I need a property about that operation that I'm performing.
我用到了哪个不等式性质
It has to be a monotonic transformation.
对 是单调变换
Here what I'm using is that log is a monotonically increasing function.
这里 lg函数是个单调递增的函数
That is important.
这很重要
If I multiply both sides by -1, which is a decreasing function,
如果不等式两边同时乘以-1 也就是说
the inequality would have to get flipped.
递减函数的话 不等关系就应该倒过来
The fact that the inequality is not flipping here,
这里不等关系不需要倒过来
I need to know that log is monotonically increasing.
因为lg函数是单调递增的
If you see log that's true.
有lg 这关系就对了
We need to be careful here.
这里我们要注意下
Now we need some approximation of n factorial
现在我们需要知道n的阶乘的近似值
in order to figure out what its log is.
因为要计算它的lg值
Does anyone know a good approximation for n factorial?
有人知道n阶乘的近似值公式吗
Not necessarily the equation but the name.
知道公式名字也行
Stirling's formula.
斯特林公式
Good.
非常好
You all remember Stirling.
看样你们都知道斯特林公式
And I just need the highest order term, which I believe is that.
这里只需要斯特林公式的最高阶因子
N factorial is at least (n/e)^n.
n阶乘大于等于(n/e)ⁿ
So, that's all we need here.
这就是我们要的
Now I can use properties of logs to bring the n outside.
现在我可以用lg的性质把n提出来
This is n lg (n/e).
等于 nlg(n/e)
And then lg (n/e) I can simplify.
这里lg(n/e)也可以化简
That is just lg n - lg e.
等于 lgn-lg(e)
So, this is n(lg n - lg e).
这里等于 n(lgn-lg(e))
Lg e is a constant,
lg(e) 是个常数
so it's really tiny compared to this lg n which is growing within.
n趋于无穷大时lg(e)可以忽略不计
This is Omega(n lg n).
最后等于Ω(nlgn)
All we care about is the leading term.
因为我们只关心前面的部分
It is actually Theta(n lg n),
其实也就是 Θ(nlgn)
but because we have it greater than
但这里是大于等于的关系
or equal to all we care about is the omega.
我们只用Ω就行了
A theta here wouldn't give us anything stronger.
Θ和Ω在这里差不多
Of course, not all algorithms have n lg n running time
当然 不是所有的排序算法的运行时间都是nlgn
or make n lg n comparisons.
或都做nlgn 次比较
Some of them do, some of them are worse,
其中一些算法是 另一些要差一点
but this proves that all of them
这个过程证明了所有排序算法
require a height of at least n lg n.
对应的决策树的深度至少是nlgn
There you see proof, once you observe the fact about the number of leaves,
如果你能想到叶节点数目的两个关系
and if you remember Stirling's formula.
还有斯特林公式 你就能完成证明
So, you should know this proof.
你们应该记住这个证明
You can show that all sorts of problems
几乎所有的排序问题都至少
require n lg n time with this kind of technique,
需要做nlgn次比较
provided you're in some kind of a decision tree model.
如果它们能对应上决策树的话
That's important.
这是一个很重要的性质
We really need that our algorithm can be phrased as a decision tree.
一个排序算法必须能够对应一个决策树
And, in particular, we know from this transformation
我们从这个转换过程知道
that all comparison sorts can be represented as the decision tree.
基于比较的排序可以转换成决策树
But there are some sorting algorithms
但是有一些排序算法
which cannot be represented as a decision tree.
无法以决策树的形式表现出来
And we will turn to that momentarily.
我马上就要讲到这种算法
But before we get there
但在讲这之前
I phrased this theorem as a lower bound on decision tree sorting.
再看下决策树的下界问题
But, of course, we also get a lower bound on comparison sorting.
也称为基于比较的排序算法的下界问题
And, in particular,
具体来讲 它说明了
it tells us that merge sort and heapsort are asymptotically optimal.
归并排序和堆排序算法是渐进最优的
Their dependence on n, in terms of asymptotic notation,
说到渐进 这些算法是依赖于n的
so ignoring constant factors,
并且忽略常数因子
these algorithms are optimal in terms of growth of n,
这些算法随n的递增趋于最优
but this is only in the comparison model.
这仅适用于基于比较的模型
So, among comparison sorting algorithms,
所以 在基于比较的排序算法中
which these are, they are asymptotically optimal.
它们都是渐进最优的
They use the minimum number of comparisons up to constant factors.
它们只比较最少的次数
In fact, their whole running time is dominated
它们的运行时间主要受
by the number of comparisons.
比较次数的影响
It's all Theta(nlgn).
比较次数都等于Θ(nlgn)
So, this is good news.
这是个好消息
And I should probably mention a little bit about
我还得说一点
what happens with randomized algorithms.
随机算法方面的东西
What I've described here really only applies,
我要讲的这些仅适用于
in some sense, to deterministic algorithms.
确定性的算法
Does anyone see what would change with randomized algorithms
有没有人发现对于随机算法有什么不同
or where I've assumed
或者我在哪里默认了
that I've had a deterministic comparison sort?
我用的是确定性的比较排序
This is a bit subtle.
只有一点差别
And I only noticed it reading the notes this morning, oh, wait.
我也是今早看讲义时发现这点的
I will give you a hint.
给你们点提示
It's over here, the right-hand side of the world.
在右边这块的黑板上
If I have a deterministic algorithm,
一个确定性的算法
what the algorithm does is completely determinate at each step.
它执行的每一步都是完全确定的
As long as I know all the comparisons that it made up to some point,
只要我能知道所有的比较情况
it's determinate what that algorithm will do.
那么这个算法基本上就是确定的
But, if I have a randomized algorithm,
但对于随机算法
it also depends on the outcomes of some coin flips.
它会受一些随机因素的影响
Any suggestions of what breaks over here?
有没有看出来二者有什么不同
There is more than one tree, exactly.
不只一棵树 完全正确
So, we had this assumption that we only have one tree for each n.
我们已假定对于每个n都只有一棵树
In fact, what we get is a probability distribution over trees.
但事实上我们得到是树的概率分布
For each value of n,
对于每个n
if you take all the possible executions of that algorithm,
把算法所有可能的执行情况
all the instruction traces,
所有执行路径
well, now, in addition to branching on comparisons,
还有比较分支
we also branch on whether a coin flip came out heads or tails,
分支中各种可能的微小变化
or however we're generating random numbers
以及如何产生随机数等等都考虑进去
it came out with some value between 1 and n.
最后会得到1到n之间的一个值
So, we get a probability distribution over trees.
我们得到了一个树的概率分布
This lower bound still applies, though.
这个下界仍然适用
Because, no matter what tree we get, I don't really care.
不管得到一个什么样的树
I get at least one tree for each n.
对于每个n至少会产生一棵树
And this proof applies to every tree.
而这个证明适用于各种树
So, no matter what tree you get,
所以不管什么样的树
if it is a correct tree
只要是正确的
it has to have height Omega(nlgn).
它的高度就是Ω(nlgn)
This lower bound applies even for randomized algorithms.
这个下界同时也适用于随机算法
You cannot get better than n lg n,
你不可能比nlgn还好
because no matter what tree it comes up with,
因为不管什么样的树
no matter how those coin flips come out,
发生什么样的变化
this argument still applies.
这个下界定理始终适用
Every tree that comes out has to be correct,
每个树都是这样
so this is really at least one tree.
这里是说至少一棵树
And that will now work.
我们现在知道了这个定理
We also get the fact that
我们还知道随机快速排序
randomized quicksort is asymptotically optimal in expectation.
在理想的情况下是渐进最优的
But, in order to say that randomized quicksort is asymptotically optimal,
为了证明它是渐进最优的
we need to know that
我们必须了解
all randomized algorithms require Omega(nlgn) comparisons.
所有随机算法都要Ω(nlgn)次比较
Now we know that so all is well.
这块讲的差不多了
That is the comparison model.
这就是基于比较的模型
Any questions before we go on? Good.
还有什么问题么 好 我们继续
The next topic is to burst outside of the comparison model
下面要讲的是对比较模型的一个突破
and try to sort in linear time.
我们要尽量在线性时间内完成排序
It is pretty clear that,
我们知道
as long as you don't have some kind of a parallel algorithm
如果不用并行算法
or something really fancy,
或是什么超能力
you cannot sort any better than linear time
你不可能比线性时间更快完成排序
because you've at least got to look at the data.
因为你得去遍历这些数据
No matter what you're doing with the data,
无论你对这些数据做什么
you've got to look at it, otherwise you're not sorting it correctly.
你必须遍历 否则你无法对其正确排序
So, linear time is the best we could hope for.
因此线性时间是我们能期望的最好结果
nlgn is pretty close.
nlgn相当接近了
How could we sort in linear time?
我们如何在线性时间内排序
Well, we're going to need some more powerful assumption.
我们需要一些更有效的设想
And this is the counter example.
这是一个计数实例
We're going to have to move outside the comparison model
我们将要不再用比较的方式
and do something else with our elements.
而是对元素做一些其他操作
And what we're going to do is assume that
我们要做的是假设
they're integers in a particular range,
它们是在特定范围内的整数
and we will use that to sort in linear time.
我们会利用这点来在线性时间内排序
We're going to see two algorithms for sorting faster than nlgn.
我们现在看两种比nlgn快的排序算法
The first one is pretty simple,
第一种很简单
and we will use it in the second algorithm.
并且我们第二种也中会用到它
It's called counting sort.
它被成为计数排序
The input to counting sort is an array, as usual,
通常计数排序的输入是一个数列
but we're going to assume what those array elements look like.
但我们会设定这些数列元素的范围
Each A[i] is an integer from the range of 1 to k.
每个A[i]是一个在1到k范围的整数
This is a pretty strong assumption.
这是一个很强的假设
And the running time is actually going to depend on k.
实际上运行时间也会依赖于k
If k is small it is going to be a good algorithm.
如果k很小这将是个很好的算法
If k is big it's going to be a really bad algorithm, worse than n lg n.
如果k很大这会是个比nlgn差的算法
Our goal is
我们的目标是
to output some sorted version of this array.
输出这个数列的某个排序序列
Let's call this sorting of A.
我们称其为A排序
It's going to be easier to write down the output directly
直接写出输出序列
instead of writing down permutation for this algorithm.
要比写出算法的排列更方便
And then we have some auxiliary storage.
因而我们需要一些辅助存储序列
I'm about to write down the pseudocode,
我接下来要写下伪代码
which is why I'm declaring all my variables here.
因此我在声明所有变量
And the auxiliary storage will have length k,
以及写下长度为k的辅助存储序列
which is the range on my input values.
这其实就是输入序列的范围长度
Let's see the algorithm.
我们来看算法
This is counting sort.
这就是计数排序
And it takes a little while to write down
这需要一些时间写下
but it's pretty straightforward.
但确实很容易明白
First we do some initialization.
首先我们做一些初始化
Then we do some counting.
然后我们计数
Then we do some summing.
然后我们求和
And then we actually write the output.
然后我们就能写出输出序列了
Is that algorithm perfectly clear to everyone?
所有人都明白这个算法了吗
No one.Good.
没人 好吧
This should illustrate how obscure pseudocode can be.
这说明了伪代码会令人费解到何种程度
And when you're solving your problem sets,
当你们在解决自己的算法问题时
you should keep in mind
你们应当记住
that it's really hard to understand an algorithm
要理解一个仅给出类似伪代码的
just given pseudocode like this.
算法是多么困难
You need some kind of English description of what's going on because,
你需要某种自然语言描述当前情形
while you could work through and figure out what this means,
因为除此以外当你想搞清楚这些问题
it could take half an hour to an hour.
你可能要耗费半个到一个小时
And that's not a good way of expressing yourself.
而这不是种自我表达的好方法
And so what I will give you now is the English description,
因此我现在要告诉你们的就是英语描述
but we will refer back to this to understand.
但我们会回顾伪代码来理解
This is sort of our bible
某种程度上
of what the algorithm is supposed to do.
这就是我们算法该做什么的圣经
Let me go over it briefly.
我来简短回顾下
The first step is just some initialization.
第一步是某些初始化
The C[i]'s are going to count some things, count occurrences of values.
C[i]用来记录某些数值出现的频率
And so first we set them to zero.
因此将它们初始化为0
Then, for every value we see A[j],
然后对于每个A[j]的值
we're going to increment the counter for that value A[j].
我们会递增代表A[j]的计数器的值
Then the C[i]s will give me the number of elements equal
最后C[i]会给出
to a particular value i.
等于数值i的元素的数量
Then I'm going to take prefix sums,
然后我会对前缀做加法
which will make it so that C[i] gives me the number of keys,
这使得C[i]表示
the number of elements less than or equal to [i]
小于或等于i的元素数目
instead of equals.
而不是等于i的数目
And then, finally,
最后我们获得了足够的信息
it turns out that's enough to put all the elements in the right place.
可以把所有元素放到正确的地方
This I will call distribution.
我把这称为分配
This is the distribution step.
这是分配的步骤
And it's probably the least obvious of all the steps.
这很可能是所有步骤中最令人迷糊的
And let's do an example
我们来做一个实例
to make it more obvious what's going on.
更清楚的观察它的运作
Let's take an array A = [4, 1, 3, 4, 3].
取一个数组A=[4,1,3,4,3]
And then I want some array C.
然后我取一个数组C
And let me add some indices here
我在这加一些下标
so we can see what the algorithm is really doing.
使得我们能看到算法实际上在做什么
Here it turns out that all of my numbers are in the range 1 to 4,
显然所有元素在1到4的范围内
so k = 4.
因此k=4
My array C has four values.
C数组有四个值
Initially, I set them all to zero.
开始我设它们均为0
That's easy.
这很简单
And now I want to count through everything.
现在我要计算所有元素
And let me not cheat here.
我不会在这里作弊
I'm in the second step, so to speak.
我在第二个步骤 打个比方
And I look for each element in order.
我要依次遍历各个元素
I look at the C[i] value.
对应每个C[i]的值
The first element is 4, so I look at C[4].
第一个元素是4 因此我看C[4]
That is 0.
那是0
I increment it to 1.
我将它加为1
Then I look at element 1.
然后我看到元素1
That's 0.
那是0
I increment it to 1.
我将它加为1
Then I look at 3 and that's here.
然后我看到元素3 在这
It is also 0.
它也是0
I increment it to 1.
我将它加为1
Not so exciting so far.
目前这并不值得兴奋
Now I see 4, which I've seen before,
现在我看到4 这我之前看到过
how exciting.
很兴奋啊
I had value 1 in here, I increment it to 2.
这里值是1 我将它加为2
Then I see value 3, which also had a value of 1.
然后我看到3 也有一个值1
I increment that to 2.
我将它加为2
The result is [1,0,2,2].
结果是[1,0,2,2]
That's what my array C looks like at this point in the algorithm.
这时C数组看上去就是这样
Now I do a relatively simple transformation of taking prefix sums.
现在我加上前缀 做个简单的改变
I want to know, instead of these individual values,
我想知道的不是这些单独的值
I wana know the sum of this prefix,
而是这些前缀数的和
the sum of this prefix,
这些这些还有这些
the sum of this prefix and the sum of this prefix.
以此类推
I will call that C prime just so
我这个数组为C'
we don't get too lost in all these different versions of C.
我们就不会混淆
This is just 1.
这是1
And 1 plus 0 is 1.
1加0是1
1 plus 2 is 3.
1加2是3
3 plus 2 is 5.
3加2是5
So, these are sort of the running totals.
因此某种程度上这些是流动的总数
There are five elements total,
总共有五个数
there are three elements less than or equal to 3,
小于或等于3的有三个元素
there is one element less than or equal to 2, and so on.
小于或等于2的有一个元素 等等
Now, the fun part, the distribution.
现在有意思的环节来了 分配
And this is where we get our array B.
这是得到B数列的地方
B better have the same size,
B最好有相同大小
every element better appear here somewhere
每个元素会在某处出现
and they should come out in sorted order.
它们会以排好的序列出现
Let's just run the algorithm.
我们来运行算法
j is going to start at the end of the array
j会从数组尾部开始
and work its way down to 1, the beginning of the array.
递减至数组头部1
And what we do is we pick up the last element of A, A[n].
我们做的就是取出A的最后元素A[n]
We look at the counter.
我们看计数器
We look at the C vector for that value.
在C数组中找到相应值
Here the value is 3, and this is the third column, so that has number 3.
这里值是3 第三列 因此3在那
And the claim is that's where it belongs in B.
而这说明了这个元素在B中的位置
You take this number 3, you put it in index 3 of the array B.
你取出3放到数列B中下标为3的地方
And then you decrement the counter.
然后减去计数器
I'm going to replace 3 here with 2.
在这用2代替3
And the idea is these numbers tell you where those values should go.
这个想法其实是这些数会告诉你值该放哪
Anything of value 1 should go at position 1.
任何值为1的元素应该到位置1
Anything with value 3 should go at position 3 or less.
任何值为3的元素应该到位置3或更靠前
This is going to be the last place that a 3 should go.
这是元素3该去的最靠后的位置
And then anything with value 4 should go at position 5 or less,
任何值为4的元素应该到位置5或更靠前
definitely should go at the end of the array because 4 is the largest value.
到了数组最末 因为4是最大的值
And this counter will work out perfectly
这个计数器会完美的运转
because these counts have left enough space in each section of the array.
因为在数组各部分都留下了足够的空间
Effectively, this part is reserved for ones,
事实上这部分留给元素1
there are no twos, this part is reserved for threes,
没有2 这部分留给元素3
and this part is reserved for fours.
这部分留给元素4
You can check if that's really what this array means.
你可以检查这个数列到底意味着什么
Let's finish running the algorithm.
我们结束运行这个算法
That was the last element.
这是最后一个元素
I won't cross it off, but we've sort of done that.
我不会划掉它 但我们确实那样做了
Now I look at the next to last element.
现在我看最后一个元素的相邻元素
That's a 4.
一个4
Fours go in position 5.
4该去位置5
So, I put my 4 here in position 5 and I decrement that counter.
因此我把这个4放在位置5并减去计数器
Next I look at another 3.
接下来看到另一个3
Threes now go in position 2, so that goes there.
现在3该去位置2 因此去那
And then I decrement that counter.
减去计数器
I won't actually use that counter anymore,
实际上我不会再用到计数器
but let's decrement it because that's what the algorithm says.
但还是减去它 因为算法规定如此
I look at the previous element.
我看到前面的元素
That's a 1.
一个1
Ones go in position 1, so I put it here and decrement that counter.
1该去位置1 放到那并减去计数器
And finally I have another 4.
最终我碰到另一个4
And fours go in position 4 now, position 4 is here,
4该去位置4 在这
and I decrement that counter.
减去计数器
So, that's counting sort.
这就是计数排序
And you'll notice that all the elements appear and they appear in order,
你会发现所有的元素出现并已排好序
so that's the algorithm.
这就是这个算法
Now, what's the running time of counting sort?
现在计数排序的运行时间是多少
kn is an upper bound.
kn是一个上限
It's a little bit better than that.
这个算法比kn要好些
Actually, quite a bit better.
事实上好了很多
This requires some summing.
这需要一些加法
Let's go back to the top of the algorithm.
回到算法开始
How much time does this step take? k.
这步需要多少时间 k
How much time does this step take?n.
这步呢 n
Each of these operations in the for loops is taking constant time,
每项for循环中的操作耗费固定时间
so it is how many iterations of that for loop are there?
这由for中的循环次数决定
And, finally, this step takes n.
最终这步需要n
So, the total running time of counting sort is k + n.
因此计数排序总的运行时间是k+n
And this is a great algorithm if k is relatively small,
如果k相对较小则此算法极好
like at most n.
比如k最大为n
If k is big like n^2 or 2^n or whatever,
如果k较大像n²或2ⁿ或任何其他
this is not such a good algorithm,
这不是那么好
but if k = O(n) this is great.
但如果k=O(n)这极好
And we get our linear time sorting algorithm.
我们得到了线性时间的排序算法
Not only do we need the assumption that our numbers are integers,
我们不仅需要假设这些数是整数
but we need that the range of the integers is pretty small
还需要确保这些整数的范围很小
for this algorithm to work.
算法在此基础上运行
If all the numbers are between 1 and order n
如果所有的数在1和n之间
then we get a linear time algorithm.
那么我们就得到了一个线性时间算法
But as soon as they're up to n lg n we're toast.
但只要他们小于nlgn我们就该满意了
We're back to n lg n sorting.
如果回到nlgn的排序
It's not so great.
就不那么好
So, you could write a combination algorithm that says, well,
因此你可以写一个混合算法
if k is bigger than n lg n, then I will just use merge sort.
如果k比nlgn大那么我就用归并排序
And if it's less than n lg n I'll use counting sort.
如果它比nlgn小我会用计数排序
And that would work, but we can do better than that.
这可行 但我们可以做的更好
How's the time?
时间怎么办
It is worth noting that we've beaten our bound,
应该注意到我们越过了界限
but only assuming that we're outside the comparison model.
但只需假设我们在比较模型之外
We haven't really contradicted the original theorem,
实际上我们还没有与原来的定理发生矛盾
we're just changing the model.
只是改变了模型
And it's always good to question
提出质疑总是好的
what you're allowed to do in any problem scenario.
对于任何题目场景中你允许做的
In, say, some practical scenarios,
某个实用的场景
this would be great if the numbers you're dealing with are, say,
如果你在处理的数字长度为1字节
a byte long.
这就很好
Then k is only 2^8, which is 256.
k仅为2⁸ 这是256
You need this auxiliary array of size 256,
你需要的辅助数列长度为256
and this is really fast.
这很快
256+n,
256+n
no matter how big n is it's linear in n.
无论n多大这是n的线性时间
If you know your numbers are small, it's great.
如果你知道数字小这会很好
But if you're numbers are bigger,
但如果数字更大
say you still know they're integers
即使你知道它们仍是整数
but they fit in like 32 bit words,
但它们是类似于32位的双字
then life is not so easy.
就不那么简单了
Because k is then 2^32,
因为k是2³²
which is 4.2 billion or so, which is pretty big.
这是42亿或此类相当大的数
And you would need this auxiliary array of 4.2 billion words,
你所需的辅助序列就要有42亿个字
which is probably like 16 gigabytes.
这大概是16G
So, you just need to initialize that array before you can even get started.
因此初始化数组都很困难
Unless n is like much, much more than 4 billion
除非n比40亿大很多很多
and you have 16 gigabytes of storage just to throw away,
而且你有16G的存储空间来纯粹挥霍
which I don't even have any machines with 16 gigabytes of RAM,
而我还没有一台机器的RAM有16G
this is not such a great algorithm.
显然这不是一个好的算法
Just to get a feel, it's good, the numbers are really small.
如果数确实小 仅凭感觉它就是好的
What we're going to do next is come up with a fancier algorithm
接下来我们要接触一个更有趣的算法
that uses this
这个算法会利用计数排序
as a subroutine on small numbers
作为小数据规模的子程序
and combines this algorithm to handle larger numbers.
结合这个算法去处理更大规模的数字
That algorithm is called radix sort.
这个算法叫做基数排序算法
But we need one important property of counting sort
不过现在要讲计数排序一个重要性质
before we can go there.
在进一步之前
And that important property is stability.
这个重要性质是稳定性
A stable sorting algorithm preserves the order of equal elements,
一个稳定性算法保证了相等元素的顺序
let's say the relative order.
这个叫相对顺序
This is a bit subtle because usually we think of elements just as numbers.
这个有点儿微妙因为通常元素就是数字
And, yeah, we had a couple threes and we had a couple fours.
现在有一对3然后还有一对4
It turns out, if you look at the order of those threes
结果是你要是看一下那些3的顺序
and the order of those fours, we kept them in order.
还有4的顺序 他们保持了原来的顺序
Because we took the last three and we put it here.
把最后的3拿出来放在这里
Then we took the next to the last three
然后拿挨着的下一个3
and we put it to the left of that
然后把它放在这个左面
where O is decrementing our counter
计数器减0
and moving from the end of the array to the beginning of the array.
然后从数组结尾挪到数组的开头
No matter how we do that, the orders of those threes are preserved,
不管怎么操作那些3的顺序都不变
the orders of the fours are preserved.
那些4的顺序也不变
This may seem like a relatively simple thing,
这个相对看起来挺简单的
but if you look at the other four sorting algorithms we've seen,
不过看一下我们讲过的其他四种排序算法
not all of them are stable.
不是所有都稳定
So, this is an exercise.
一个课堂练习
Exercise is figure out which other sorting algorithms
找出讲过的其他排序算法
that we've seen are stable and which are not.
哪些稳定哪些不是
I encourage you to work that out
我强烈建议你做出来
because this is the sort of thing that we ask on quizzes.
因为这种问题会在小测中出现
But for now all we need is that counting sort is stable.
不过现在知道计数排序是稳定的就够了
And I won't prove this, but it should be pretty obvious from the algorithm.
我不证明了不过从算法看来很显然
Now we get to talk about radix sort.
现在开始基数排序
Radix sort is going to work for
基数排序是用来在
a much larger range of numbers in linear time.
线性时间内处理大范围数据的
Still it has to have an assumption about how big those numbers are,
现在还是要假设这个数据有多大
but it will be a much more lax assumption.
不过肯定是很宽松的假设
Now, to increase suspense even further,
现在再留点儿悬念
I am going to tell you some history about radix sort.
我准备讲一下基数排序的历史
This is one of the oldest sorting algorithms.
这是最古老排序方法之一
It's probably the oldest implemented sorting algorithm.
很可能是最古老实现的算法了
It was implemented around 1890.
大约出现在1890年
This is Herman Hollerith.
这是Herman Hollerith
Let's say around 1890.
大约1890
Has anyone heard of Hollerith before?
有人以前听说过Herman Hollerith么
A couple people.
两个
Not too many.
不多啊
He is sort of an important guy.
他是个很重要的人物
He was a lecturer at MIT at some point.
他曾经是MIT的讲师
He developed an early version of punch cards.
他发明了最早版本的打孔卡片
Punch card technology.
打孔卡片技术
This is before my time so I even have to look at my notes to remember.
我也没用过 所以看了讲义才想起来
Oh, yeah, they're called punch cards.
它们叫打孔卡片
You may have seen them.
你们可能也见过
If not they're in the PowerPoint lecture notes.
如果你们没见过 看一下ppt课件
There's this big grid.
这是个大网格
These days, if you've used a modern punch card recently,
如果你最近用过现代打孔卡片的话
they are 80 characters wide and, I don't know,
他们是80字符宽 我不知道
I think it's something like 16, I don't remember exactly.
好像是16吧 记不清了
And then you punch little holes here.
然后在这里打小孔
You have this magic machine.
用这个神奇的机器
It's like a typewriter.
像一个打字机
You press a letter and that corresponds to some character.
你按下一个键对应一个字母
Maybe it will punch out a hole here, punch out a hole here.
可能会在这里打一个洞
You can see the website if you want to know exactly
想深入了解的话可以上网看一下
how this works for historical reasons.
它具体工作方式和历史原因
You don't see these too often anymore, but this is in particular the reason
你也不用了解太多 不过这个确实是
why most terminals are 80 characters wide because that was how things were.
大部分终端是80字符宽的原因
Hollerith actually didn't develop these punch cards exactly,
不能确切的说Hollerith发明了这种打孔卡片
although eventually he did.
虽然确实是他发明了打孔卡片
In the beginning, in 1890, the big deal was the US Census.
早在1890年 人口普查很困难
If you watched the news, I guess like a year or two ago,
如果你看新闻的话 我想应该一两年前
the US Census was a big deal
人口普查很困难
because it's really expensive to collect all this data from everyone.
因为从每个人那里收集数据确实很庞大
And the Constitution says you've got to collect data
宪法说你必须收集
about everyone every ten years.
关于每个人每十年的数据
And it was getting hard.
而且越来越困难
In particular, in 1880, they did the census.
特别是 那是1880年 人口普查
And it took them almost ten years to complete the census.
可能要耗费将近十年时间才能完成
The population kept going up,
人口持续增长
and ten years to do a ten-year census,
用10年时间做一次十年普查
that's going to start getting expensive when they overlap with each other.
当两次普查时间重叠时 代价变得很高
So, for 1890 they wanted to do something fancier.
所以1890年他们想要做点儿特别的事情
And Hollerith said,
然后Hollerith说了
OK, I'm going to build a machine that you take in the data.
好吧 我准备建一个能输入数据的机器
It was a modified punch card
这个就是一个修改过的打孔卡片
where you would mark out particular squares depending on your status,
根据你的状态标记相应的方块
whether you were single or married or whatever.
你是未婚啊还是已婚啊或者什么的
All the things they wanted to know on the census
所有普查时需要知道的数据
they would encode in binary onto this card.
他们在卡片上编码成二进制
And then he built a machine
然后Hollerith就做了一个机器
that would sort these cards so you could do counting.
可以对那些卡片进行分类以便进行统计
And, in some sense, these are numbers.
某种感觉上 这些都是数字
And the numbers aren't too big,
这些数字不是太大
but they're big enough that counting sort wouldn't work.
但又确实大到足以让计数排序算法失效
I mean if there were a hundred numbers here,
我是说如果这里有100个数字
2^100 is pretty overwhelming, so we cannot use counting sort.
2¹⁰⁰实在太猛了 所以不能用计数排序
The first idea was the wrong idea.
首先 我的想法一开始就是错误的
I'm going to think of these as numbers.
我准备把它们当成数字
Let's say each of these columns is one number.
每一列是一个数字
And so there's sort of the most significant number out here
就是对这个最高位在这里
and there is the least significant number out here.
和最低位在这里的数字排序
The first idea was you sort by the most significant digit first.
第一个想法是先对最高位排序
That's not such a great algorithm,
这个不是一个好的算法
because if you sort by the most significant digit
因为如果对最高位排序
you get a bunch of buckets each with a pile of cards.
会得到一堆卡片在一堆桶里面
And this was a physical device.
而且这个是物理设备
It wasn't exactly an electronically controlled computer.
不是电子计算机
It was a human that would push down some kind of reader.
需要交给一些人来读
It would see which holes in the first column are punched.
他会看第一列哪个洞被打上了
And then it would open a physical bin
然后他打开一个箱子
in which the person would sort of swipe it
把这个卡片扔进去
and it would just fall into the right bin.
然后这个卡片就被放在正确的箱子里了
It was a semi-automated.
这是半自动的
I mean the computer was the human plus the machine, but never mind.
计算机是人加上机器 不过没关系
This was the procedure.
就是这个过程
You sorted it into bins.
你把它们放在箱子里面排序
Then you had to go through and sort each bin by the second digit.
然后还得对每个箱子的卡片按第二位排序
And pretty soon the number of bins gets pretty big.
很快箱子数目变得非常多
And if you don't have too many digits this is OK,
如果不想要这么多位 也可以
but it's not the right thing to do.
不过这本来就不是正确的方案
The right idea, which is what Hollerith came up with after that,
Hollerith后来提出 正确的做法是
was to sort by the least significant digit first.
先对最后一位排序
And you should also do that using a stable sorting algorithm.
这里你必须使用一种稳定的排序算法
Now, Hollerith probably didn't call it a stable sorting algorithm
当时Hollerith可能不会叫它稳定排序
at the time, but we will.
不过我们可以
And this won Hollerith lots of money and good things.
这个算法让Hollerith赚了很多钱
He founded this tabulating machine company in 1911,
它在1911年发明了这个制表机
and that merged with several other companies to form something
然后在1924年吞并了几个公司
you may have heard of called IBM in 1924.
组成了叫做IBM的新公司
That may be the context in which you've heard of Hollerith,
这个可能是你听说过Hollerith的原因
or if you've done punch cards before.
也可能你之前做过打孔卡片
The whole idea is that we're doing a digit by digit sort.
整体思想就是 按位排序
I should have mentioned that at the beginning.
我一开始就说IBM的话你们就知道了
And we're going to do it from least significant to most significant.
我们从最低位开始到最高位
It turns out that works.
结果这个算法很有用
And to see that let's do an example.
来看一个例子
I think I'm going to need a whole two boards ideally.
我想我可能需要两块黑板才够
First we'll see an example.
首先我们来看一个例子
Then we'll prove the theorem.
然后我们将证明这个方法
The proof is actually pretty darn easy.
证明实际上非常简单
But, nonetheless, it's rather counterintuitive this works
尽管如此 这个算法确实不容易想到
if you haven't seen it before.
如果你以前没见过的话
Certainly, the first time I saw it, it was quite a surprise.
当然 我第一次见到的时候也很惊讶
The nice thing also about this algorithm is there are no bins.
最出色的地方在于这个算法没有箱子
It's all one big bin at all times.
始终都是一个大箱子
Let's take some numbers.
我们取一些数字
This is a three digit number.
这是一个三位数
I'm spacing out the digits so we can see them a little bit better.
我在数字中间留空 以便看清楚每一位
657, 839, 436, 720 and 355.
657 839 436 720和355
I'm assuming here we're using decimal numbers.
我假设这是十进制的
Why not?
没什么不好
Hopefully this are not yet sorted.
希望它们还是乱序
We'd like to sort them.
因为我们就是要为它们排序
The first thing we do is take the least significant digit,
首先取出最低位
sort by the least significant digit.
按照最低位排序
And whenever we have equal elements like these two nines,
遇到相等的数 比如这两个9
we preserve their relative order.
我们保持它们的顺序
So, 329 is going to remain above 839.
所以329仍然要在839的前面
It doesn't matter here because we're doing the first sort,
这没关系 因为现在才是第一遍
but in general we're always using a stable sorting algorithm.
不过通常我们总是选择稳定排序算法
When we sort by this column, first we get the zero,
根据这一列排序 首先是0对应的数
so that's 720, then we get 5, 355.
也就是这个720 然后是5 355
Then we get 6, 436.
然后是6 436
Stop me if I make a mistake.
出错的话打断我一下
Then we get the 7s, and we preserve the order.
然后是这些7 保持它们原来的顺序
Here it happens to be the right order,
这里顺序恰好已经正确
but it may not be at this point.
不过最后可能不是这样
We haven't even looked at the other digits.
我们甚至还没看其它位呢
Then we get 9s, there are two 9s, 329 and 839.
然后是9 2个9 329和839
All right so far?
目前为止没问题吧
Good.
好的
Now we sort by the middle digit, the next least significant.
现在按中间位排序 也就是倒数第二位
And we start out with what looks like the 2s.
看起来2是最小的
There is a 2 up here and a 2 down here.
上面有一个2在这 下面一个2在这
Of course, we write the first 2 first, 720, then 329.
当然 先写第一个2 720然后329
Then we have the 3s, so we have 436 and 839.
然后是3 得到436和839
Then we have a bunch of 5s it looks like.
然后看起来是一堆5
Have I missed anyone so far?
目前为止没漏掉哪个数吧
No. Good.
没有 好的
We have three 5s, 355, 457 and 657.
有3个5 355 457和657
I like to check that I haven't lost any elements.
我来检查一下有没有漏掉
We have seven here, seven here and seven elements here.
这里7个 这里7个 这里也是7个
Good.
好的
Finally, we sort by the last digit.
最后 我们对剩下的这一位排序
One thing to notice, by the way, is before we sorted by the last digit -
请注意 在我们按这一位排序之前
Currently these numbers don't resemble sorted order at all.
这些数字看起来一点也不像排过序的
But if you look at everything beyond the digit we haven't yet sorted,
但是如果不去看没有排序过的这一位
so these two digits, that's nice and sorted,
这两位 很好 是有序的
20, 29, 36, 39, 55, 57, 57.
20 29 36 39 55 57 57
Pretty cool.
很好
Let's finish it off.
把这个做完
We stably sort by the first digit.
对第一位稳定排序
And the smallest number we get is a 3, so we get 329 and then 355.
最小的是3 得到329 然后355
Then we get some 4s, 436 and 457,
然后是4 436和457
then we get a 6, 657, then a 7, and then we have an 8.
然后是6 656 然后一个7一个8
And check.
检查一下
I still have seven elements.
还是7个数
Good. I haven't lost anyone.
好的 没丢啥
And, indeed, they're now in sorted order.
确实 它们现在已经排好序了
And you can start to see why this is working.
你可以想一想为什么这样做能行
When I have equal elements here, I have already sorted the suffix.
当有相同元素时 后缀数字已经排好了
Let's write down a proof of that.
接下来是证明过程
What is nice about this algorithm is we're not partitioning into bins.
好的部分是我们不用分成一个一个箱子了
We always keep the huge batch of elements in one big pile,
而是始终把它们放在一整个大桶里面
but we're just going through it multiple times.
我们只是多次遍历
In general, we sort of need to go through it multiple times.
通常 排序总是需要多次遍历
Hopefully not too many times.
只希望次数不要太多
But let's first argue correctness.
先证明正确性
To analyze the running time is a little bit tricky here
分析运行时间有点儿小技巧
because it depends how you partition into digits.
因为这个取决于你怎么分割位
Correctness is easy.
正确性证明很简单
We just induct on the digit position that we're currently sorting,
只要对已经排序的部分数字位进行归纳
so let's call that t.
这里记作t
And we can assume by induction that it's sorted beyond digit t.
通过归纳假设在t之前的位已经排序
This is our induction hypothesis.
这是归纳假设
We assume that we're sorted on the low-order t - 1 digits.
假设我们已经对较低的t-1位排好序了
And then the next thing we do is sort on the t-th digit.
接下来做的就是对第t位排序
We just need to check that things work.
然后检查先后顺序对不对
And we restore the induction hypothesis for t instead of t - 1.
我们用t-1的表达式来计算t
When we sort on the t-th digit there are two cases.
对第t位排序有两种情况
If we look at any two elements, we want to know
检查任意两个元素 我们想知道
whether we put them in right order。
这两个元素的相对顺序是否正确
If two elements are the same,
如果这两个元素是相同的
let's say they have the same t-th digit
就是说它们有相同的第t位数字
- This is the tricky case.
这就是用到一点技巧的地方
If they have the same t-th digit then their order should not be changed.
第t位数字相同意味着不应交换顺序
So, by stability, we know that they remain in the same order
基于稳定性原则 可知它们保持原顺序
because stability is supposed to preserve things
因为被排序元素具有相同的键值时
that have the same key that we're sorting on.
稳定性意味着保持元素位置不变
And then, by the induction hypothesis,
然后 根据归纳假设
we know that that keeps them in sorted order
我们可以知道它们仍然保持有序
because induction hypothesis says that they used to be sorted.
因为根据归纳假设它们已经排过序
Adding on this value in the front
加上现在这个第t位数字
that's the same in both doesn't change anything
还是有序的 因为没有改变任何东西
so they remain sorted.
所以它们仍然是有序的
And if they have differing t-th digits -- --
如果它们有不同的第t位数字
then this sorting step will put them in the right order.
那么排序过程将把它们调整为正确的顺序
Because that's what sorting does.
因为那就是排序的本职工作
This is the most significant digit,
这是最高位
so you've got to order them by the t-th digit if they differ.
所以我们可以根据第t位对它们排序
The rest are irrelevant.
其余的无关紧要
So, proof here of correctness is very simple once you know the algorithm.
所以如果知道算法 正确性很容易证明
Any questions before we go on?
现在 有什么问题吗
Good.
很好
We're going to use counting sort.
下面我们将使用计数排序
We could use any sorting algorithm we want for individual digits,
对一位数字 我们可以使用任何排序算法
but the only algorithm that we know
但是目前我们所知的算法里
that runs in less than n lg n time is counting sort.
运行时间少于nlgn的只有计数排序
So, we better use that one to sort of bootstrap
所以 我们最好还是用它做辅助算法
and get an even faster and more general algorithm.
这样才能实现更快更一般的算法
I just erased the running time.
我刚刚擦掉了运行时间
Counting sort runs in order k + n time.
计数排序运行时间为(n+k)阶
We need to remember that.
我们需要牢记这一点
And the range of the numbers is 1 to k or 0 to k - 1.
数字的范围是1到k或者0到(k-1)
When we sort by a particular digit,
当我们仅对一位数字排序时
we shouldn't use n lg n algorithm
不应该使用nlgn的算法
because then this thing will take n lg n for one round
因为这将在每一轮花费nlgn时间
and it's going to have multiple rounds.
而我们必然会运行很多轮
That's going to be worse than n lg n.
结果将比nlgn糟糕
We're going to use counting sort for each round.
因此我们将在每一轮使用计数排序
We use counting sort for each digit.
对每一位上的数字使用计数排序
And we know the running time of counting sort here is order k + n .
已知基数排序的运行时间是(k+n)
But I don't want to assume that my integers are split into digits for me.
但我不想按照每一个数字位来依次排序
That's sort of giving away too much flexibility.
那样将会丧失太多灵活性
Because if I have some number written in whatever form it is,
因为数可以用任意形式来表示
probably written in binary,
比如用二进制表示的数
I can cluster together some of those bits and call that a digit.
可以把几个比特放在一起当做一位来处理
Let's think of our numbers as binary.
假设我们的数是二进制数
Suppose we have n integers.
有n个整数
And they're in some range.
它们都在相同的范围内
And we want to know how big a range they can be.
而我们希望知道它们的取值范围
Let's say, a sort of practical way of thinking,
从实践角度来考虑
you know, we're in a binary world, each integer is b bits long.
我们知道 二进制整数设为b比特长
So, in other words, the range is from 0 to 2b - 1.
那么取值范围就在0到(2^b-1)之间
I will assume that my numbers are non-negative.
假定所有的数都非负
It doesn't make much difference if they're negative, too.
有负数的话情况也没有太大不同
I want to know how big a b I can handle,
我希望知道我们可以处理多大的b
but I don't want to split into bits as my digits
但是我不想把数字拆分成比特
because then I would have b digits
因为虽然我得到了b个数字
and I would have to do b rounds of this algorithm.
但是我需要重复b轮这个算法
The number of rounds of this algorithm is the number of digits that I have.
重复的轮数就是数的位数
And each one costs me, let's hope, for linear time.
比较好的情况下 每次要花费线性时间
And, indeed, if I use a single bit, k = 2.
而实际上如果只是1比特 那么k=2
And so this is order n.
所以这是n阶的
But then the running time would be order n per round.
但是每轮的运行时间都是n阶的
And there are b digits,
一共有b位数字
if I consider them to be bits, order n times b time.
如果按比特切分 则有n乘b阶的时间
And even if b is something small like log n,
即使b是很小的值 比如lgn
if I have log n bits,
如果我们有lgn比特
then these are numbers between 0 and n - 1.
则这些数在0到(n-1)之间
I already know how to sort numbers
我已经知道怎样在线性时间内
between 0 and n - 1 in linear time.
对0到(n-1)之间的数排序
Here I'm spending n lg n time, so that's no good.
这里花费了nlgn时间 这不好
Instead,
相反地
what we're going to do is take a bunch of bits and call that a digit,
我们要做的是把连续的比特看做一位
the most bits we can handle with counting sort.
我们可以用计数排序一次处理的最多比特
The notation will be I split each integer into b/r digits.
算法是 把每个整数拆分为b/r位数字
Each r bits long.
每个数字是r比特长
In other words, I think of my number as being in base 2^r.
换句话说 基于2^r进制来表示这个数
And I happen to be writing it down in binary,
我只是碰巧用二进制形式将它们写下来
but I cluster together r bits
但是我把r比特放在一起
and I get a bunch of digits in base 2^r.
实际是基于2^r进制得到了一些数字
And then there are b/ r digits.
然后我们一共有b/r位数字
This b/r is the number of rounds.
b/r是我们需要运算的轮数
And this base --This is the maximum value I have in one of these digits.
而这个基数 就是每一位数字的最大值
It's between 0 and 2^r.
就是说每位数字的范围在0到2^r之间
This is, in some sense, k for a run of counting sort.
某种意义上说 它就是计数排序中的k
What is the running time?
那么 总的运行时间怎么算呢
Well, I have b/r rounds.
我们一共有b/r轮
It's b/r times the running time for a round.
那么是b/r乘以每轮运行所需时间
Which I have n numbers and my value of k is 2^r.
我们有n个数字 k值为2^r
This is the running time of counting sort, n + k,
计数排序的运行时间是(n+k)
this is the number of rounds, so this is b/r (n+2^r).
这是轮数 最终结果为(b/r)*(n+2^r)
And I am free to choose r however I want.
而我们可以任意挑选r
What I would like to do is minimize this run time over my choices of r.
目的是通过选择r来尽量减少运行时间
Any suggestions on
有没有什么建议呢
how I might find the minimum running time over all choices of r?
怎样挑选r可以使运行时间最小呢
Techniques, not necessarily solutions.
方法就可以 不必说出完整的过程
We're not used to this because it's asymptomatic,
我们一下子想不到是因为它是隐式的
but forget the big O here.
但是如果忽略这里的大O的话
How do I minimize a function with respect to one variable?
怎样求一个一元函数的最小值呢
Take the derivative, yeah.
对 求导
I can take the derivative of this function by r,
我们对这个函数关于r求导
differentiate by r, set the derivative equal to 0,
对r求导 求导数为零时的解
and that should be a critical point in this function.
就可以得到函数的驻点
It turns out this function is unimodal in r
实际上这个函数在r上是单模的
and you will find the minimum.
因此总可以找到最小值
We could do that.
我们可以算出来
I'm not going to do it because it takes a little bit more work.
我不具体写出来了 这会花费一些时间
You should try it at home.
你下课以后可以写一下
It will give you the exact minimum,
这里 我们可以得到具体的最小值
which is good if you know what this constant is.
如果你知道了这个常数是多少
Differentiate with respect to r and set to 0.
对r求导 求导数等于零时的解
I am going to do it a little bit more intuitively,
我将会采用某种更直觉的方法
in other words less precisely,
换句话说 不那么精确的方法
but I will still get the right answer.
但我们还是可以得到正确的结果
And definitely I will get an upper bound
准确的说是上界
because I can choose r to be whatever I want.
因为r是任意选择的
It turns out this will be the right answer.
所以这个结果总是正确的
Let's just think about growth in terms of r.
让我们考虑关于r的增长过程
There are essentially two terms here.
这里有两个包含r的项
I have b/r(n) and I have b/r(2^r).
我们有(b/r)*(n)和(b/r)*(2^r)
Now, b/r(n) would like r to be as big as possible.
对于(b/r)*(n)这项 r越大越好
The bigger r is the number of rounds goes down.
r越大轮数越少
This number in front of n, this coefficient in front of n goes down,
n前面的这个数 这个系数变小
so I would like r to be big.
所以我希望r尽可能大
So, b/r(n) wants r big.
所以 (b/r)*(n)希望r尽可能大
However, r cannot be too big.
然而 r不能太大
This is saying I want digits that have a lot of bits in them.
因为那意味着一个数用很长的比特来表示
It cannot be too big because there's 2^r term out here.
它不可以太大 因为这里有2^r项
If this happens to be bigger than n
如果这个值恰好比n大
then this will dominate in terms of growth of r.
这一项将决定多项式随r的增长而增大
This is going to be b times 2 to the r over r.
结果将是b*(2^r)/r
2 the r is much, much bigger than r,
2^r远远大于r
so it's going to grow much faster is what I mean.
增长速度远比我们想象得快
And so I really don't want r to be too big for this other term.
因此根据这一项可知 r不能太大
So, that is b/4(2^r) wants r small.
所以 b/r*(2^r)希望r比较小
Provided that this term is bigger or equal to this term
注意到这一项大于等于这一项
then I can set r pretty big for that term.
则由这一项可知 r可以取较大的值
What I want is the n to dominate the 2^r.
我们要的是让n决定整个多项式的大小
Provided I have that then I can set r as large as I want.
在这样的前提下我才可以任意设定r的值
Let's say I want to choose r to be maximum subject to this condition
所以不妨选择r为这种情况下的最大值
that n is greater than or equal to 2^r.
也就是满足n大于等于2^r
This is an upper bound to 2^r, and upper bound on r.
这是2^r的上界 就得到r的上界
In other words, I want r = lg n.
换句话说 r最大可以取lgn
This turns out to be the right answer up to constant factors.
在现有条件下 这个结果是对的
There we go.
继续
And definitely choosing r to be lg n will give me an upper bound
选择r=lgn就可以得到
on the best running time I could get
运行时间的上界
because I can choose it to be whatever I want.
因为我可以任意选择
If you differentiate you will indeed get the same answer.
如果你用求导的方法 结果是一样的
This was not quite a formal argument but close,
这并不是严格的解答 但是结果很接近
because the big O is all about what grows fastest.
因为大O记号只关心谁增长最快
If we plug in r = lg n we get bn/lg n.
代入r=lgn 就得到(b*n)/lgn
The n and the 2^r are equal,
n等于2^r
that's a factor of 2, 2 times n, not a big deal.
它是2的倍数 2乘以n 没有太大关系
It comes out into the O.
经过大O记号之后
We have bn/lg n which is r.
我们得到了(b*n)/lgn 其中lgn=r
We have to think about what this means
我们需要考虑这是什么
and translate it in terms of range.
并且把它转换成数的范围
b was the number of bits in our number,
b是数的比特位数
which corresponds to the range of the number.
对应于数的取值范围
I've got 20 minutes under so far in lecture so I can go 20 minutes over, right?
原来我总共提早20分下课 所以今天我打算拖堂20分
No, I'm kidding.
不是啦 我开玩笑的
Almost done.
马上就下课
Let's say that our numbers, are integers are in the range,
注意到待排序数列都是某个范围内的整数
we have 0 to 2^b, I'm going to say that it's range 0 to nd.
这个范围是0到2^b 或者说0到n^d
This should be a -1 here.
这里应该有一个-1
If I have numbers that are between 0 and n^d - 1
如果数的范围在0到n^d-1
where d is a constant or d is some parameter,
这里的d是常数 也就是参数
so this is a polynomial in n,
那么这就是n的多项式
then you work out this running time.
计算一下运行时间
It is order dn.
是(n*d)阶的
This is the way to think about it
就是这样来考虑
because now we can compare to counting sort.
现在我们可以和计数排序比较
Counting sort could handle
计数排序可以用线性时间
0 up to some constant times d in linear time.
处理0到某个常数乘以d范围内的数
Now I can handle
现在我们可以在线性时间内处理
0 up to n to some constant power in linear time.
0到n的某个常数次方范围内的数
This is if d = order 1 then we get a linear time sorting algorithm.
如果d=O(1) 这就是一个线性时间的算法
And that is cool as long as d is at most lg n.
而且只要d小于等于lgn就可以
As long as your numbers are at most n lg n
只要数的范围在nlgn以内
then we have something that beats our n lg n sorting algorithms.
我们就可以击败原来的nlgn算法
And this is pretty nice.
这样很好
Whenever you know that
只要我们知道
your numbers are order log n bits long we are happy,
我们的数字是lgn比特长 我们就很高兴
and you get some smooth tradeoff there.
我们做了一些实际情况的权衡
For example, if we have our 32 bit numbers
比如 如果我们有32位的数
and we split into let's say eight bit chunks
我们把它们拆分为 比如8位的段
then we'll only have to do four rounds each linear time
我们仅仅需要做四轮线性时间的运算
and we have just 256 working space.
只需要256位辅助空间
We were doing four rounds for 32 bit numbers.
32位数需要4轮
If you use n lg n algorithm,
如果使用nlgn算法
you're going to be doing lg n rounds through your numbers.
你需要做lgn次运算
n is like 2000, and that's at least 11 rounds for example.
n差不多是2000 那么至少是11轮
You would think this algorithm is going to be
你会认为这个算法对于小的数字
much faster for small numbers.
会运行得更快
Unfortunately, counting sort is not very good on a cache.
不幸的是 计数排序在缓存上要求更多
In practice, rating sort is not that fast an algorithm
在实践中 计数排序并不那么快
unless your numbers are really small.
除非你的数都很小
Something like quicksort can do better.
快速排序之类的会做得更好
It's sort of shame, but theoretically this is very beautiful.
有点遗憾 在理论上这个算法真的很美
And there are contexts
但是需要在正确的情境下
where this is really the right way to sort things.
才适合使用这种方式来排序
I will mention finally that if you have arbitrary integers
最后提一下 如果是对任意整数排序
that are one word length long.
并且每个数都是一个字长
Here we're assuming that there are b bits in a word
这里我们假设每个字有b比特
and we have some depends indirectly on b here.
这里我们间接地有些依赖b
But, in general,
但是 一般来说
if you have a bunch of integers and they're one word length long,
如果你有一些一个字长的数
and you can manipulate a word in constant time,
而且可以在常数时间内操作一个字的话
then the best algorithm we know for sorting
目前已知的最好的排序算法
runs in n times square root of lg lg n time expected.
期望运行时间是n乘根号下lg(lgn)
It is a randomized algorithm.
这是一个随机算法
We're not going to cover that algorithm in this class.
我们在本课程内不会涉及它
It's rather complicated.
它非常复杂
I didn't even cover it in Advanced Algorithms when I taught it.
甚至我教的高级算法也不会讲
If you want something easier,
如果你想要某种简单一些的算法
you can get n times lg lg n time worst-case.
有一个最坏情况n乘lg(lgn)的算法
And that paper is almost readable.
那篇论文还是可以看懂的
I have taught that in Advanced Algorithms.
我在高级算法里讲了那个算法
If you're interested in this kind of stuff,
如果你对这些感兴趣
take Advanced Algorithms next fall.
下学期可以选修高级算法
It's one of the follow-ons to this class.
那是本课程的后继课程
These are much more complicated algorithms,
有很多非常复杂的算法
but it gives you some sense.
但是它们可以给你某种信息
You can even break out of the dependence on b,
你可以打破对b的依赖
as long as you know that b is at most a word.
只要你知道b最多是一个字长
And I will stop there unless there are any questions.
没有问题的话就到这里
Then see you Wednesday.
下周三再见